A Guide to the Fletcher Harris Archer Papers, 1842-1894
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Fletcher Harris Archer Papers, 1842-1894
Library of Virginia
38801
0.225 cubic feet
Fletcher Harris Archer
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 28 January 2000 and 7 February 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
Fletcher Harris Archer was born 6 February 1817 in Petersburg, Virginia, to Allen Archer and Prudence Whitworth Archer. He attended schools in Petersburg, then the University of Virginia, from where he graduated in 1841. Archer returned to Petersburg and began his law career. Captain of the 7th Company, 39th Virginia Militia, he raised a company for service during the Mexican war. His company went to Mexico in 1847 and served under General Zachary Taylor (1784-1850) until the end of the war. When Virginia seceded in 1861, Archer raised a company named "Archer Rifles," part of the 12th Virginia Infantry. Archer was promoted to lieutenant colonel in the army before retiring in May 1862. In 1864, Archer became a major in the Virginia Reserves during the Petersburg campaign. His reserve battalion was responsible for helping prevent the Union's capture of Petersburg in June 1864. Archer remained with the Confederate army until its surrender in 1865, and he returned to Petersburg to resume his law career. Archer served as mayor of Petersburg from 1882 to 1883. He married first Eliza Ann Eppes Allen (d. 1851) and they had 1 daughter. He married Martha Georgianna Morton Barksdale 31 March 1863, and they had no children. Archer died 21 August 1902 in Petersburg, and was buried in Blandford Cemetery.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1842-1894, of Fletcher Harris Archer, attorney, Mexican War officer, Confederate army officer, and Petersburg mayor, and his family, including business records, correspondence, and suit papers. The business records include an account book, accounts, and receipts, primarily of Allin Archer, Fletcher's father and a miller in Petersburg. The letters are from friends, family, and business associates, covering myriad topics, such as family, religion, school, weather, crops, court cases, legal matters, business affairs, and politics. Of note are the letters concerning the disputed Petersburg mayoral election of 1882 between Archer and Thomas J. Jarratt (1817-1895). Also includes the constitution and by-laws of the Association of United Volunteers, a Mexican War veterans organization for members of Companies D and E of the Virginia Regiment of Volunteers, and a list of instructions, ca. 1869, for registering voters and working at the polls.
Contents List
- Account Book, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1859-1862, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Association of United Volunteers - Constitution and By-Laws, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters, 1842-1849 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters, 1856-1858 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters, 1860-1862, 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters, 1871-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters, 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters, 1890-1894 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Suit Papers (Box 1, Folder 12)